就喺麦太快要临盆嘅时候
When Mrs. McBing was in labour…
有一个胶兜喺九龙上空飞过
A pan appeared in the sky.
沿住荔枝角道直出大角咀道
It flew along Garden Street…
经过好彩酒家再左转返出花园街乐园牛丸王对上⋯
Turned left, and stopped at the Beef ball King.
都系唔好：
Correction:
先去街市大楼嗰间妹记鱼腩粥嗰度
It first arrived at the Market Building…
转下，转下⋯都系唔好：
Lingered a bit… Correction:
都系出返去亚皆老街飞过火车桥右转入太平道
It flew over the railway, turned right…
再右转抹返出去窝打老道向女人街方向飞下下⋯
And headed directly for the Bazaar.
飞下，飞下⋯
It flew on…
最后胶兜飞咗入广华医院嘅候产房
At last coming into the maternity ward.
亦即系麦太右边魂精对上⋯
There, on the right hand side of Mrs. McBing.
都系唔好：左边魂精对上⋯
Correction: Left hand side.
转下，转下，转下噉⋯
The pan stayed.
麦太认定呢个系异像
Mrs. McBing, convinced that this was a miracle,
于是向魂精对上嘅胶兜许愿
Made a wish…
而脑入面亦即时出现咗快要出世个仔嘅样⋯
Thinking of her soon-to-be-born son.
希望佢好聪明，读书好叻！
Please make him a clever and smart boy!
胶兜对麦太嘅愿望似乎冇咩表示
The pan didn't seem to hear her words.
于是佢对住胶兜补充噉话：
So Mrs. McBing amended her wish:
或者读书唔叻，出嚟做嘢叻啦？
Or make him a smart businessman?
又或者呢⋯
Or maybe…
又或者系好靓仔，好靓仔
Or make him really handsome.
好似周润发，同埋梁朝伟咁靓仔！
As handsome as Chow Yun Fat or Tony Leung!
胶兜依然系噉喺度转，好似一啲应承嘅迹象都冇
The pan didn't respond.
麦太一时心虚
Mrs. McBing, in panic…
嗱嗱嗱喺胶兜未落地之前起过另外一个愿望：
Made a final amendment:
就算唔系咁聪明同咁靓仔，只要福星高照
Her boy needed not to be smart or handsome
一世够运，乜嘢事都逢凶化㗎喇！
As long as luck be with him!
佢靠自己有料解决啲嘢就梗系好啦
It's nice to depend on oneself…
不过运气都好紧要㖞
But luck is essential still.
虽然似梁朝伟周润发都行运定咗
Of course Chow and Leung are lucky guys…
但系都要叻仔先得㗎！
But then they are smart too!
最后，胶兜「嘀督」一声咁落地
Finally, the pan dropped to the floor…
嘀督？嘀督㖞，即系应承啦
Mrs. McBing, believing her wish granted…
麦太心谂，今次冇死喇！
Thought that was magnificent!
但你应承咗啲咩呢？
But what had the pan granted her?
叻仔？好运？
A smart boy? A lucky boy?
定系话似周润发啊？
Or a Chow look-alike?
为咗纪念呢个赐福嘅胶兜
To commemorate this, Mrs. McBing…
麦太决定将个仔嘅名叫做麦胶
Decided to name her son McNificient.
都系唔好，胶胶声，咁难听！
No! It's better to be humble!
不如叫麦兜啦！
I'll name him McDull!
各位⋯
Dear all…
我就系呢个差少少就叫做麦胶嘅小朋友⋯
I am the boy, no more McNificient…
麦兜！
I'm McDull!
“My School”
咦，麦太，咩唔见你一排
Oh dear,
个脚瓜囊粗咗咁多呀？
your calves have grown strong.
鬼咩，日日扑嚟扑去⋯
I've been desperately…
同我仔揾幼稚园吖嘛！
looking for a school!
点解唔试下好彩酒楼斜对面
Why not try the one…
旧中侨百货公司楼上嗰间⋯
at the Emporium?
春田花花幼稚园呢？
The Spring Flower Kindergarten?
就系坐落喺界限街同南昌街交界⋯
Yeah! The one at the junction…
银城美食广场附近嗰间⋯
Right next to Silver City Food Mall.
春田花花幼稚园呀？
The Spring Flower Kindergarten!
系呀！深水埗地铁站口行过去唔使十分钟呀！
Only 10 minutes walk from the MTR Station!
春田花花幼稚园，师资优良⋯
Spring Flower Kindergarten, good environment…
仲系西人教英文添㗎！
With white teachers for English class!
咦，西人教英文？
White teachers for English class?
系呀！
Yeah!
春田花花，真系好多西人㗎！
Spring Flower offers white teachers!
〝鹅满是快烙滴好耳痛⋯〞
“We are all happy children…”
〝鹅闷天天一戏个窗！〞
“We sing everyday!”
〝鹅们在壳习，鹅闷载升胀⋯〞
“We learn as we grow…”
〝鹅闷是春天滴化！〞
“We are the flowers of spring!”
呢个扮紧白兔猪样嘅小朋友⋯
This piggy kid in a rabbit outfit…
即系横睇掂睇都唔似发哥或者伟仔嗰个呢⋯
Who doesn't look the least like Chow or Leung…
就系我，麦兜
That's me, McDull.
呢间就系我读嘅幼稚园
This is my kindergarten.
校长系潮州人
The headmaster came from the countryside…
可能仲系讲紧潮州话嘅
As a result, he speaks with an accent.
所以咁多年嚟⋯
For many years…
我其实唔系好知佢噏乜
I had difficulty hearing him.
蛋挞！　　蛋挞！
- Tart!    - Tart!
荔芋火鸭扎！　　荔芋火鸭扎！
- Duck dumpling!    - Duck dumpling!
唔好忘记校训九十七⋯　　唔好忘记校训九十七⋯
- The 97 Rule…    - The 97 Rule…
都唔可以忘记校训九十八！
Shall be replaced by the 98 Rule!
各位同学⋯
Good, children!
今次早会系要同大家分享
We are sharing an important issue…
一个可重要嘅主题：
this morning:
小朋友，你哋今个月交咗学费咩呀？
Children, have you handed in the school fee?
交！
Yes!
哎，好在！噉大家可以返去上堂喇
Great! Now move to class.
你哋可能觉得呢间幼稚园好烂
You might conclude that this is a shabby school.
但系，对于我同埋我班同学仔嚟讲
But, for me and my mates…
呢度系我哋最快乐，最美丽嘅乐园⋯
This is the most beautiful paradise!
⋯仲有一个好疼我哋
…Also, there is Miss Chan.
不过就有少少游魂嘅班主任Miss Chan
Who adores us in her absent-minded way.
佢嘅志愿系做下一个王菲
Also, she is a Faye Wong wannabe.
或者系做下一个陈慧琳都得
Actually, Kelly Chan will do!
好喇，我哋而家开始点名
Roll call now.
麦唛同学！　　到！
- McMug!    - Present!
亚辉同学！　　到！
- Fai!    - Present!
菇时同学！　　到！
- Goosie!    - Present!
得巴同学！　　到！
- Darby!    - Present!
阿May同学！　　到！
- May!    - Present!
阿June同学！　　到！
- June!    - Present!
阿May同学！　　到！
- May!    - Present!
麦唛同学！　　到！
- McMug!    - Present!
阿May同学！
May!
Miss Chan，你点咗我两次喇！
Miss Chan, I've been called twice!
啊，系咩？
Oops!
校长早晨！
Good morning, sir!
校长再见！
Good day, sir!
好，我哋而家继续点名
Back to roll call.
阿June同学！　　到！
- Fai!    - Present!
亚辉同学！　　到！
得巴同学！　　到！
- Darby!    - Present!
阿May同学！　　到！
- May!    - Present!
麦唛同学！　　到！
- McMug!    - Present!
菇时同学！　　到！
- Goosie!    - Present!
好，仲有边个未点？
Have I missed anyone?
麦兜！
McDull!
麦兜同学！
麦唛呀，即系呢⋯
Hey, I don't understand…
妈妈啊，我个心总系印住印住⋯
I keep feeling that…
好似有人嗌紧我个名噉嘅
Someone is calling me.
你哋唔好以为我心散啊
Don't think that I've been daydreaming.
其实我系喺度思考紧一啲学术性嘅问题：
I was contemplating something academic:
点解橙叫「疴－烂－煮」呢？
How does this universe work?
妈妈话食橙会通大便
I mean, I ate 6 oranges that morning…
「疴」呢个我明白，但系「烂－煮」呢？
And my stomach wouldn't stop.
仲有呢个「芭－娜－哪」香蕉啊
Then I ate 3 bananas this morning.
点解雨伞会叫做「暗－芭－娜－哪」呢？
Again my stomach wouldn't stop…
嗱，我「暗」啦，噉我「暗」嗰条蕉
It just wouldn't stop!
至多会疴烂煮啫，点解会搞到落雨呢？
How are these two things related?
呢个世界仲有好多嘢我谂唔明
There are so many things that I don't understand.
不过我唔怕
But I am not afraid.
我谂，到我读完幼稚园
One day, when I finish kindergarten…
升埋小学，上到中学
I shall move up…
再入埋大学⋯
And get my degree.
等我大学毕业嗰阵
When I graduate from university, I know…
我谂我乜都会明白晒！
I shall understand everything!
到嗰阵⋯
And then …
我买层楼畀我妈妈！
I will buy my mother a house!
喺幼稚园楼下，校长兼营嘅间茶餐厅
Our headmaster runs a tea stand…
我哋一班同学仔放咗学都经常去傍衬
Which we kids frequent after class.
唔该，鱼蛋粗面啊　　冇粗面噃
- Fishball noodle, please.    - No noodle left.
噉啊⋯要碗鱼蛋河粉啊　　冇鱼蛋噃
- Fishball rice noodle then.    - No fishball left.
噉啊⋯要金钱肚粗面啊　　冇粗面噃
- Chicken wing noodle then.    - No noodle left.
噉啊咁要鱼蛋油面啊　　冇鱼蛋噃
- How about fishball congee?    - No fishball left.
乜样样都冇嘅？
Nothing left today?
噉要墨鱼丸粗面啊　　冇粗面噃
- How about beef noodle?    - No noodle left.
又冇啊？
Again?
噉唔该畀碗鱼蛋濑啊　　冇鱼蛋噃
- Fried chicken wing with fishball…    - No fishball left.
麦兜啊，佢哋啲鱼蛋同粗面卖晒㗎啦
Hey, fishball and noodle are both gone…
即系所有要鱼蛋或者粗面嘅配搭都冇㗎啦
You can't combine them with other things.
噢，冇嗰啲配搭啊？
Can't combine them?
噉唔该，净鱼蛋啊　　冇鱼蛋噃
- A bowl of fishball then.    - No fishball left.
净粗面呢？　　冇粗面噃
- A bowl of noodle?    - No noodle left.
睇到呢度⋯
By now…
大家大概都知道我有几叻仔嘞
you can probably tell how smart I am.
嗰阵我无忧无虑，冇乜所谓－－
Nothing worried me, all things were fine.
冇鱼蛋咩？粗面都好啊
No fishball left? Let's get some noodle.
麦兜，转身食啊！
Shoot, Dull!
睇住自己日日疴烂煮⋯
Watching myself grow and grow…
日日长肉⋯
Every day…
感到充满力量！
I feel full of strength!
世界好美丽！
The world is beautiful!
有一首歌，Miss Chan唱得好好听呀
There is a song Miss Chan loves…
我成日想学习
Which I always want to learn…
但系唱嚟唱去都系「疴﹣兰﹣煮」咁「芭﹣娜﹣娜」噉⋯
But it just comes out different.
系唔系All Things Bright and Beautiful呀？
You mean “All Things Bright and Beautiful”?
系呀，所有嘢都几好喇！
Yes, all are fine!
世上一切⋯
All things on earth…
所有嗰啲嘢，都几好！
They are fine!!
1，2，3，4，5，6，7⋯
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7…
多劳多得！
No pain no gain!
星期一至星期七⋯多劳多得！
Monday till Sunday… No pain no gain!
呢个嗌得特别劲嘅中年母猪
The middle-aged swine is Mrs. McBing,
就系我妈妈麦太
my mother…
我妈妈真系好劲呀
A brilliant woman…
一个女人揹起成个世界！
carrying the world!
系呀，我妈妈真系好犀利㗎
Yes, she is really something.
除咗做保险，地产经纪同埋trading之外⋯
She works in insurance, real estate and trading.
佢仲趁住高科技热潮搞咗个煮𩠌嘅网站⋯
At the height of IT, she even sets up her cooking site…
www．麦太世界．com
www.MrsMcBing.com
佢煮嘅𩠌，一样咁犀利
Offering brilliant dishes.
欢迎大家收睇＜麦太世界＞
Welcome to “Mrs. Mc Can Cook”.
今日我为大家介绍个⋯
Today we're doing a simple dish,
简单又别致嘅小菜纸包鸡
Paper Chicken.
家里头嘅小朋友一定好喜欢㗎
Kids at home would love it.
材料系好简单：我哋只需要一个鸡包
The ingredient: a chicken bun.
我哋将黐喺鸡包底嘅纸撕出嚟⋯慢慢撕
Slowly, we tear the paper away from the bun
咁就会得到一张鸡包纸喇
Now we have a bun paper.
然后将鸡包纸一反反转
Turn the paper over like this…
呢味纸包鸡就完成喇，系咪好易整啦？
Voila! Simple, isn't it?
多谢大家收睇
Thank you, everyone!
好高兴咁快又同大家见面
How time flies since the last episode!
跟住落嚟我会教大家整一味纸鸡包
Now we shall do a Paper Bun.
材料都好简单，只需要白纸一张
The ingredient takes only a piece of paper.
我哋只需要张张纸咁样⋯
Do it like this…
一个纸鸡包就咁完成咗喇
And we have a Paper Bun.
各位小朋友，你哋话似唔似鸡包啊？
Isn't this a lovely bun?
间阵要教大家一味几别致嘅小菜－
A novelty today for everyone:
包鸡纸包鸡包纸包鸡
Chicken Bun Paper Bunning a Bun.
首先将纸包鸡小心噉撕开
First, unwrap the chicken from the paper.
大家就会有一张纸包鸡同埋一嚿鸡啦
Now we have a paper and a piece of chicken.
跟住将鸡包纸好似我噉包住块鸡
Use the bun paper to wrap up the chicken like this…
然后再好似噉样将包鸡纸包住佢
And then wrap it like this…
咁一味「包鸡纸包鸡包纸包鸡」就完成喇！
The delicious Chicken Bun Paper Bunning a Bun!
系咪好简单呢？
Such a simple dish!
仲真系有嚿鸡食添！
See if the chicken is good!
今日要同大家介绍一味⋯
Kids are bound to love…
小朋友一定喜欢嘅⋯
today's dish…
鸡包包鸡包包鸡包纸包纸⋯
Bunning a Chicken Bun Paper…
包鸡包鸡包纸包鸡
Bunning the Paper Chicken.
做法都好简单
It takes simple work.
我哋先将鸡包包住个鸡包
Use the chicken bun to bun…
再包住个鸡包⋯
the chicken bun…
包住张鸡包纸
Then use the chicken bun paper to…
再包包包包包住个纸鸡包
bun and bun…
再包包包，纸纸纸
Paper, bun, bun, paper, bun…
纸包纸，纸包鸡，鸡包纸，纸包鸡⋯
Paper, chicken, bun, bun, chicken…
不过我妈妈都有佢温柔嘅一面
But my mother has her tender side.
例如每晚临睡前，佢都会讲故事畀我听
Every night, she tells me a story before sleep.
从前，有个小朋友讲大话；有一日⋯
Once upon a time, a boy lied. One day…
佢死咗！
He died.
从前，有个小朋友好勤力读书⋯
Once upon a time, a boy studied hard.
佢长大，发咗！
He grew up and got rich.
从前，有个小朋友唔孝顺，有一日⋯
Once upon a time, a boy was naughty. One day…
佢屈亲个脚脚！
He twisted his ankle.
妈，我想瞓啦
Mother, I want to sleep.
从前，有个小朋友早睡晚起；第二朝⋯
Once upon a time, a boy slept a lot. Next day…
佢死咗！
He died.
我妈妈就系噉，一切都咁直接
That is my mother's direct approach.
佢爱得我直接⋯
Her love for me is direct.
对我嘅期望直接
Her expectation of me is direct.
佢，一、二、三、四、五、六、七
For her, it is always…
唔得都要得
“no pain no gain”.
但系如果有啲嘢，真系真系唔得呢？
But there are things that simply cannot be gained.
日子一日一日咁过
Days come and go.
首先周润发嗰单嘢⋯
Talking about Chow look-alike…
大家都唔好再提！
You still think it's going happen?
至于好运⋯
When it comes to luck…
我用我嘅童子手帮妈妈抽嘅六合彩number
The lottery numbers that mother obliges to draw…
竟然奇迹一样一个都未中过！
Failed even to bring her one cent!
叻仔？
As for being smart…
我试过好努力咁读书，但系⋯
I did try hard, but then…
但系⋯我仲可以发梦
But then, I still have dreams.
“My Ideal World”
马尔代夫，坐落于印度洋嘅世外桃源
Maldives, a world outside our world.
蓝天白云，椰林树影，水清沙幼
The sky blue, clouds white, the trees tall and water bright.
七彩缤纷嘅珊瑚，目不暇给嘅热带鱼群
The colourful world of the tropical sea.
充满住赤道热力嘅原始海洋，远离繁嚣
The primitive ocean of primitive energy.
体验热情如火嘅风土人情
Experience a world that knows no boundary!
享受一个脱俗出尘嘅梦幻之旅
Enjoy a trip to your ideal world.
犀利旅行社，旅行社牌照号码350999
Brilliant Touring Agency, license no. 350999
妈妈你知唔知到马尔代夫系边㗎？
Mother, you know where Maldives is?
啊好远㗎
Far.
有几远呀？
How far?
搭飞机至到啰
You need to fly there.
咁妈妈你会唔会走我去㗎？
Mother will you take me there?
会！得发咗先啦
One day when I am rich.
咁妈妈你几时发得呀？
When will you get rich?
呃，就快啦⋯
Soon…
发梦吖嘛！
In my dream!
校长早晨！
Good morning, sir!
校长再见！
Good day, sir!
你最喜爱嘅地方喺边度呀？
Where is your favourite place?
我最喜爱嘅地方呢，就系日本喇
My favourite place is Japan.
嗰度有 Disney 同埋 Hello Kitty
They have Disneyland and Hello Kitty Land.
我而家戴紧个发夹都系嗰边买嘅
I bought my hairpin there.
我最钟意嘅地方就系加拿大
My favourite place is Canada.
婆婆同埋舅父呀，佢哋都系加拿大㗎
Grandma and my uncles live there.
我最钟意去嘅地方就系泰国喇
My favourite place is Bangkok.
嗰度有好多水上活动㗎，仲有鱼翅食添㖞
They have water sports and shark's fin soup.
呃，我最喜爱嘅地方呢⋯
My favourite place is that…
就系嗰间咩嚟啰！
What's-its-name.
嗰度有欢乐天地啦，仲有美食广场啦
They have Fun World and Food Mall.
嗰度啲海南鸡饭好大碟㗎
Their chicken rice fills you up.
系喇系喇，嗰间叫做银城中心
Right, that's Silver City Centre.
嗰间嘢啲饭好多，好大碟㗎！
They serve huge bowls of rice.
不过讲到我最想去嘅地方呢，嗰度犀利啰
As for the place I most want to go, wow!
嗰度蓝天白云，椰林树影，水清沙幼
There, the sky is blue, clouds white, the trees tall…
座落于印度洋嘅世外桃源
It is a world outside our world.
喂，衰仔啊，快啲起身返学喇
Rise and shine, kiddo.
咦？
Oh?
妈妈！
Mother!
开啲药过佢食就冇事㗎喇
Take some medicine and he'll be fine.
医生啊，啲药食咗会唔会有嗰啲咩㗎？
Will he not what after the medicine?
唔会！
No!
噉佢食药使唔使咩啊？
Need he not what for the medicine?
唔使！同佢打多支针添呢！
No! I'll give him a shot.
吓？要打针啊？
A shot?
佢好怕打针㗎㖞
He's scared of shots.
噉佢怕唔怕死呀？
Is he scared of dying?
冇嘢吖嘛？快啲食埋啲药水佢先啦！
How are you doing? Take the medicine.
妈妈我唔想食药水呀
Mother I don't want medicine.
唔好呀妈妈，我唔食呀
Please mother, no.
我唔食士多啤梨药水呀！
I don't want the strawberry drink!
唔好喊啦，唔食药唔会好㗎
You won't get well without the medicine.
乖乖啲，病好咗妈妈带你去马尔代夫
Sweetie, we will go to Maldives once you get well.
真嘅？
Really?
妈妈几时呃过你呀？
Has mother ever lied before?
乖，食埋啲药水先啦
Now, drink up.
嘻嘻，好嘢，马尔代夫！
Yes, Maldives!
马尔代夫！
Maldives!
妈妈，咁我哋几时去呀？
Mother, when will we go?
嗯，你乖乖哋食埋啲药，好返晒啦我即刻订机票
I will book the ticket once you get well.
嚟啦，食多更！
Come on, drink up!
妈妈，你睇！
Look, mother!
妈妈你睇，我好返喇！
Mother, I am well!
啲药所以我全部食晒喇
I've taken all the medicine.
即系间屋有乜嘢唔系畀你食晒㗎？
But you've taken everything edible at home.
妈妈，呢次唔同㗎，本来咁大樽嘅
You see, the whole bottle was filled…
我饮下一格，又一格，又一格⋯
And I gulped it down bit by bit…
吓，我饮晒㖞！
I did it!
饮晒就叻仔啦！
Now I am a good boy!
饮晒就好返实啦！
Now I am not sick!
妈妈⋯
Mother…
乜嘢啊？
What?
我哋几时去马尔代夫啊？
When are we going to Maldives?
乜嘢马尔代夫啊？
Maldives?
呢，你话我返就同我去马尔代夫㗎嘛！
You said we would go once I get well.
马尔代夫呢，椰林树影，水清沙幼⋯
Maldives, where the trees tall and water bright…
座落于印度洋嘅世外桃源啦！
The world outside our world!
啊，估唔到你几好文采㗎噃
Those words have flair.
讲得几好听啊！
I am happy for you.
妈妈我唔系讲喇㗎，又系你话嘅⋯
Mother, you promised…
你话我病好咗之日就同我去马尔代夫㗎！你讲过㗎！
We'd go to Maldives once I get well.
我话发咗先至同你去㗎
I meant once I get rich.
唔系㖞，妈妈你话好咗就同我去㗎㖞
No, that wasn't what you meant.
你明明讲过好返就同你去马尔代夫㗎㖞
You said we'd go once I get well.
你讲过㗎！
You promised!
得啦得啦，唔好喊啦
Now stop crying.
同你去马尔代夫啦
We will go to Maldives.
真嘅？　　系啊
- Really?    - Yes.
咁几时去啊？
When?
等我发咗先啰
Once I get rich.
你发咗㗎喇，你发咗㗎喇⋯
But you are rich.
系喇系喇系喇，发咗喇
Sure, sure, I am rich.
下个礼拜同你去啦，得未啊？
We will go next week, OK?
好嘢！
Bravo!
喂，麦唛啊，我系麦兜啊
This is McDull.
即系呢，我明日就要飞喇
Hey, I'm leaving tomorrow.
系啊　　⋯系咩？
- Yes…    - Is that right?
飞机餐好难食㗎？
The food on board is horrible?
但点都要食㗎啦！
Be it so!
唔通自己带嘢上去食咩？
We couldn't bring our own food, right?
仲讲哦？
Still chatting away?
快啲嚟执埋啲行李先啦哦
You need to pack.
你帮我话畀佢哋知，我明日去马尔代夫喇
Tell them I'm going to Maldives tomorrow.
嗰度蓝天白云，椰林树⋯
Where the trees tall and water bright…
水清净沙有！
Hey, you!
我嚟紧㗎喇！
Coming!
我要执行李喇，返嚟先再同你倾过啦
I need to pack now. Talk to you later.
拜拜！
See you!
哎哟，妈妈，我系咪要带埋出世纸去㗎？
Mother, do I need to bring my birth certificate?
都要㗎
I guess so.
咁成绩表呢？
And school report?
成绩表又唔使
We don't need that.
好嘢！吓得我啊！咁都好啲
Wow, I'm saved!
揾到喇！
I found it!
出世纸俾我揾返到喇！
I found my birth certificate!
妈咪你帮我收好佢，唔好掉咗佢呀
Mother, you keep it and don't lose it…
掉咗就去唔到㗎喇
Or else we're stuck.
早机去，晚机返
Leave on the morning, return at night.
妈妈话噉先最著数
Mother said that'd make things worthy.
就系噉样⋯
Hence…
我过咗我小时候最著数⋯
The most beautiful day in my childhood experience…
最完美嘅一日
Passed.
噉你话，纸包唔包得住鸡呢？
Do you think paper is a good chicken wrapper?
都得嘅⋯
Maybe.
尤其系细细旧嗰啲
If only for one small piece.
妈妈早唞！
- Goodnight, mother!    - Goodnight!
啱啱收到消息
The Hong Kong…
奥运滑浪风帆选手李丽珊以五场四胜嘅结果
windsurfing athlete San San Li…
夺取香港历史上第一面奥运金牌！
Has just won the first gold medal in Hong Kong history!
消息话李丽珊喺知道自己稳夺奥运金牌之后
San San, when confirmed her winning…
好激动噉同在场嘅记者讲今次佢嘅成绩⋯
Told reporters that her result…
可以证明到香港嘅运动员唔系腊鸭！
Help proves that Hong Kong athletes are horrible…
各位对唔住，应该　　系垃圾，唔系腊鸭！
Excuse me, it should be “honourable”.
对唔住，应该系　　唔系垃圾，亦都唔系腊鸭！
Hong Kong athletes are honourable athletes.
特别报告完毕
End of special report.
咦，妈妈好似又有计噉噃
Then, mother seemed inspired.
靓仔，好运，叻仔呀⋯
Handsome, lucky, smart…
睇嚟都唔多靠得住
So much for those plans.
哗，好唔好靠下个手瓜噉呢？
Now how about something physical?
“Looking for Logan”
于是，一个梦都未醒⋯
And so, while one dream lingers on…
我又得到另外一个梦
Another one begins.
“aka: How Does a Calf Become a Calf?”
系咪应该系脚瓜之争
It's about the Calf!
我知道一啲都唔容易
I know it is not easy.
我知道要揾到黎根绝对唔容易
I know it is not easy to find Logan.
我知道要佢收我做徒弟更加唔容易
I know it is not easy for him to take me in.
但无论几唔容易，我都要试一试
No matter how difficult this is…
我要黎根收我做徒弟！
Logan will be my master!
无论几辛苦，我一定要攞到奥运金牌！
I shall get an Olympic medal!
长洲！长洲！
Cheung Chau!
你孕育咗珊珊！你都会孕育我！
You raised San San, now you will raise me!
当我企喺奥运会颁奖台上面
When I receive my Olympic medal…
我会举起金牌同全世界讲：
I shall tell the world:
香港运动员唔系垃圾！
HK athletes are honourable athletes!
长洲，我终于嚟到长洲嘞！
Cheung Chau, I finally make it here.
长洲，我要亲吻呢片圣洁嘅土地！
I must kiss this holy land!
小朋友呀，呢度系南丫岛噃！
Kiddo, this is Lamma Island.
南丫岛？都孕育咗周润发噃！
Lamma Island? Where Chow Yun Fat grew up?
真估唔到我黎根避入嚟南丫岛都畀你揾到
I came into hiding on this island…
小朋友，我谂你都知道乜嘢叫做狗仔队嘞？
To stay away from the paparazzi.
再加上不时有啲小朋友同埋家长嚟揾我话要拜我为师
And so many kids came to seek me out.
所以我咪过嚟南丫岛避一避
So I came to live here.
至于拜师嘅嘢⋯
You want me to be your master?
拜你个头！
Forget it!
你哋呢班住喺香港岛嘅小朋友骄生惯养
You city kids are all spoiled…
边挨得苦㗎？
Good for nothing!
想学珊珊攞奥运金牌？
You want to get an Olympic medal too?
醒梦你！
Dream on!
小朋友，你睇下！
Kiddo, look!
哗，呢只⋯
This calf…
呢只脚瓜⋯好粗好大呀！仲大个节瓜呀！
So thick, so strong!
脚瓜啲肌肉非常结实⋯
And so muscular!
啲青筋凸晒出嚟，好似钢线噉
With steely veins running down…
啲脚毛，每一条好似铁钉噉硬
Hair sticking out like wire…
脚趾公啲脚甲成吋噉厚，究竟⋯
And those tough toenails!
要行过几多座山⋯
How many hills must it travel…
跨过几多个海⋯
How many seas must it pass…
挨过几多苦头⋯
How much pain must it bear…
先至可以练成呢只举世无双嘅脚瓜？
Before a calf becomes a calf?
我⋯我一定要练成呢只脚瓜！
I shall have this calf!
师父！
Master!
我可唔可以去个小便呢？
Can I take a pee?
唔知点解每一次唱呢首歌都会急小便
Whenever I sing this song, I need to pee.
今次去定先，都怕一阵会再急过
Taking a pee first would not help.
但系我而家一定要唱呢首歌
But I must sing it now.
希望可以改变黎根对我嘅睇法
With this song, I hope…
我要用呢首歌打动黎根
Logan will think better of me.
我要黎根收我做徒弟！
Logan will be my master!
嗰首歌，系噉唱嘅⋯
The song goes like this…
「大包，整多两笼」
“Big bun, have two more…”
「大包，整多两笼唔怕滞」
“Forget about indigestion.”
「大包，整多两笼」
“Big bun, have two more…”
「大包，整多两笼唔怕滞」
“Forget about indigestion.”
「大包，整多两笼」
“Big bun, have two more…”
「大包，整多两笼唔怕滞」
“Forget about indigestion.”
「食晒个包，脚瓜大个」
“Eat the bun, grow a calf…”
「孝顺我阿妈」
“Respect my mother.”
「食晒个包，脚瓜硬朗」
“Eat the bun, toughen my calf…”
「再奉献国家」
“Serve my country.”
「大包，整多两笼」
“Big bun, have two more…”
「大包，整多两笼唔怕滞」
“Forget about indigestion.”
「大包，整多两笼」
“Big bun, have two more…”
「大包，整多两笼唔怕滞」
“Forget about indigestion.”
黎根听完首歌之后，啲表情有啲古怪⋯
Logan looks strange after the song.
我一定要好好把握呢个机会
I must grab my chance.
师父！你收我做徒弟啦！
Master! Please be my master!
你唔收我做徒弟，我呢一世都跪喺度！
Or let me kneel here forever!
起身啊！
Get up…
多谢师父！
Thank you master!
唔系啊⋯我系叫你扶我起身啊！
Silly, help me get up.
顶唔顺啊！我个脚瓜太痹啊！
My calf has gone numb!
我将今日发生嘅嘢话晒畀妈妈听
I tell mother what happened today.
妈妈佢乜嘢都冇讲到
She won't say a word…
喺冰箱度攞咗只雪鸡出嚟解冻
But starts to defrost a chicken.
晚饭时候，妈妈倒咗三杯米酒
At dinner, mother offers 3 glasses of wine…
再将几只橙同埋蒸熟咗嘅鸡放喺祖先前面
Oranges and the chicken to the ancestral tablet.
妈妈叫我跪低，向祖先请请
Mother then tells me to kneel down.
跟住，妈妈口噏噏噉讲咗一啲嘢
She mumbles something when…
然之后我哋又一齐对住祖先拜多几拜
We pay our respect to our ancestor.
妈妈蹲低身将啲酒倒喺地上面
As mother pours the wine on the floor…
庄重又温柔紧同我讲：
She says in her solemn, tender voice:
以后要生生性性
Be good,
跟师父学嘢，光宗耀祖！
learn with the master and honour the ancestor.
妈妈喺长洲揾咗间酒楼摆咗几回拜师宴
In honour of my master, mother throws a banquet.
因为我系师父最后一个入室弟子
As I am the last disciple of the master…
所以到贺嘅乡绅父老特别多
Everyone on Cheung Chau comes.
估唔到黄德森都有嚟饮
San San's lover thinks…
仲赞我背脊啲肉厚添
I have a nice thick back.
但系珊珊就去咗集训，冇嚟到
San San is in training and couldn't come.
麦唛，菇时同得巴都嚟咗
All my mates are there too…
仲带埋成绩表，奖牌同大包嚟添
Bringing school report, medals and big buns.
佢哋都希望黎根可以收埋佢哋做徒弟
They hope Logan will take them in also.
食完鸡丝翅，就到咗拜师仪式
After the soup, the ceremony begins.
妈妈斟咗杯热茶畀我，叫我畀师傅饮
Mother pours a cup of tea and I offer it to the master.
哦，我千辛万苦嚟到长洲揾黎根⋯
After all the hardship looking for Logan…
哦，我终于可以同珊珊一齐练习滑浪风帆啊！
Now I can windsurf together with San San!
我将杯茶递咗畀黎根，黎根佢⋯
I offer the tea to Logan…
师父佢饮咗杯茶，正式收咗我做徒弟嘞
He drinks the tea and becomes my master.
啲来宾睇嚟好高兴
All the guests look happy.
特别系长洲啲乡绅父老拍掌拍得特别落力
And everyone from Cheung Chau applauds.
多谢各位赏面！多谢各位！
Thank you for honouring me!
在下平生有两项称得上得意嘅绝技
In my life, I have two skills that I'm proud of.
第一样，系滑浪风帆！呢样早已
One is windsurfing.
传咗畀我外甥女珊珊啊
That I have passed onto San San.
另一项绝技，我打算传畀呢个新修嘅徒弟⋯
The other, I shall pass onto my new disciple…
希望我可以将我哋长洲人世世代代嘅传统
Let him show the world…
发扬光大！
what a marvelous skill that is!
噉请问嗰样绝技系乜嘢啊？
Can you tell us what skill is that?
第二样绝技，就系⋯
That is…
抢包山！
Bun snatching!
抢包山？
Bun snatching?
年轻嘅观众可能唔知乜嘢系「抢包山」呀
“Bun Snatching”, for our uninformed audience…
抢包山系长洲独有嘅传统节日
Is a unique Cheung Chau tradition.
每年农历四月
Each year, in the fourth month,
长洲嘅居民都会举办太平清醮
Cheung Chau people…
喺北帝庙前搭起三座包山
Set up 3 stacks of bun to celebrate.
噉乜嘢系包山呢？
Stacks of bun?
顾名思义⋯
Literally speaking…
包山就系一座由好多好多好多包砌起嘅山！
A stack of bun is a stack of many buns!
一座包山，起码六、七层楼高⋯
Each stack coming up to 6, 7 storeys.
噉你可以想像一下嗰度有几多包喇？
Imagine how high that is.
噉抢包山，自然就系要将包山嘅包抢到手！
Bun snatching is to snatch those buns!
锣鼓响起
When the time comes,
数以百计嘅青年就会一涌而上去抢包
hundreds of youth would rush up…
抢到位置越高嘅包，就代表越大嘅祝福
The higher the bun you snatch, the more blessed you are.
更加可以表现自己不凡嘅身手
And the more praises you get.
但喺1978年两座包山突然塌咗，多人重伤
In 1978, 2 stacks tumbled down, hurting many.
「抢包山」从此被禁！
“Bun Snatching” was thus banned!
长洲特有嘅传统，亦渐被遗忘
And the unique tradition is lost.
奥运金牌⋯我谂呢一世都唔会攞到
The Olympic medal… it has slipped away.
每个礼拜六我都会搭船过长洲
Every Saturday, I'd take a ferry to Cheung Chau…
去学抢包山⋯
To practice bun snatching.
一项冇奖牌，冇对手，冇比赛⋯
A game with no medal, no competitor, no competition…
甚至乎冇人知道佢系运动嘅运动
A game nobody knows of.
更衰嘅系，连包山都冇！
A game with no bun to snatch!
师傅净系叫我去佢屋企⋯
All I do is to go to the master's home…
喺个组合柜度爬嚟爬去
And crawl around the shelf.
碰！三番！
My win!
冇偷懒！继续练！
Keep going, lazy bone!
有一日，珊珊嚟咗师傅屋企！
One day, San San arrives!
珊珊！我个师姐珊珊啊！
San San, my idol!
可以见到珊珊⋯
Seeing San San…
爬得咁辛苦都系值得㗎！
Makes me forget all these weeks' hard work.
珊珊！
San San!
珊你个头啊！继续练习！
San yourself! Work!
仲唔去？
You hear me?
珊珊佢见唔到我呢个师弟
So San San leaves without seeing me.
我唯有死死气爬返上个组合柜
In despair, I crawl up the shelf.
我咁大个仔，乜嘢「头」都畀人闹过⋯
I have had a lot of things said to me…
但系「珊你个头」唔知点解特别刺耳
But “San yourself”…
hurts like never before.
我⋯我⋯
I… I…
我唔学抢包山嘞！
I am quitting!
其实今日系我第一次咁近距离同丽根见面
Today is the first time I sit down with Logan.
睇怕佢都有五十岁啦
He must be around 50,
但系仲有副孩子脸
with a baby face.
鸡尾包！啱啱出炉嘅！
Fresh from the oven!
其实鸡尾包呢⋯
This thing…
吓，你话噉样似唔似鸡尾呀？哈哈哈哈
What does it look like?
麦兜嘅学嘢呢⋯都仲可以
Dull… he's not a bad student.
跟住黎根讲咗一大堆说话⋯
Logan then proceeds to tell me a lot…
讲下佢嘅抱负，佢对麦兜嘅期望
His ambition, his expectation of Dull.
佢话会将佢识嘅嘢毫无保留噉教晒畀麦兜
He says he'll teach all he knows to Dull.
黎根越讲越兴奋
The more he talks, the more excited he gets.
佢话滑浪风帆都唔系佢最犀利嗰样
He tells me windsurfing is not his strongest.
佢最劲嘅就系抢包山
His strongest is really bun snatching…
佢话抢包山结合咗南拳
Something combining Fist,
神功戏同现代器械操
ritual and gymnastic.
佢话抢包山先至系佢呢世人最大嘅成就
He says bun snatching is his lifelong achievement.
缩嗰只脚，唔该！
Move your feet!
你睇下！
Look!
哗，呢节⋯呢节脚瓜好粗好大呀！仲大过节瓜！
This calf… so thick, so strong!
脚瓜嘅肌肉非常结实⋯
And so muscular!
啲青筋凸晒出嚟，好似钢线噉
With steely veins running down…
啲脚毛每一条都好似铁钉咁硬
Hair sticking out like wire…
脚趾公啲脚甲成寸咁厚，究竟⋯
And those tough toenails!
要行过几多座山
How many hills must it travel…
跨过几多个海
How many seas must it pass…
挨过几多苦头
How much pain must it bear…
先至可以练成呢一只举世无双嘅脚瓜？
Before a calf becomes a calf?
我个仔⋯
My son…
你个仔，第时都会有咁大只脚瓜
Your son, he will get this calf.
其实我都唔知我仔要咁粗嘅脚瓜⋯
I have no idea why would Dull need…
有咩用
such a calf.
但系见到佢一条条凸起嘅青筋，唔知点解⋯
But, looking at those steely veins…
我⋯我谂起麦兜嘅爸爸，阿炳
I am reminded of Dull's pa, Bing.
我揾完成间屋都揾唔到部电子英文词典
The electronic dictionary cannot be found.
去咗边呢？
Where could it be?
唔通⋯冇理由㗎？
Could it be that…?
咦，估唔到真系妈妈攞咗㖞．吓得我啊！
So mother has been using the dictionary?
点解妈妈会用英文写信嘅？
But why is she writing in English?
封信好短
The letter is short.
我谂妈妈佢系好辛苦用电子词典逐个逐个字译做英文
Mother must have translated it word by word.
于是我用返电子词典将封信译返做中文
I use the machine to turn it back into Chinese.
封信，原来系妈妈写畀奥委会主席㗎
It is addressed to the Olympic Committee Chairman.
「亲爱的主席：」
“Dear Chairman:”
「你好吗？我很好！」
“How are you? I am fine.”
「你吃包吗？我吃包！」
“You like bun? I like bun!”
「我们居住在香港这里的人，很爱吃包」
“We Hong Kong people here love bun.”
「小笼包，上海包，广东包，莲蓉包」
“Buns of all sort.”
「好朋友，我认为
"Dear friend,
抢劫那些包，十分重要」
it is important to snatch buns."
「也算是运动，就真！」
“It is a game, no joke.”
「要大力！大吃晚上的粥，和大节瓜！」
“One needs energy, and many night congee.”
「按照我愚蠢的见解⋯」
“In my stupid opinion…”
「抢劫嗰些包，系奥运会比赛」
“Snatching bun is an Olympic game.”
「让全世界嘅体育家，抢过！」
“Let athletes all over the world snatch!”
「世界便和平！」
“And there will be peace.”
「你有孩子吗？」
“Do you have children?”
「我有一个孩子，麦兜」
“I have a boy, Dull.”
终于讲到我啦！
She's talking about me!
「他是一个好男孩」
“He is a good boy.”
「他非常懂得抢劫那些包」
“He knows how to snatch buns.”
「有一天，我看见他，抢劫包⋯」
“One day, I can see him snatching buns…”
「抢了一个奥运金牌」
“Ending up snatching an Olympic medal.”
「哪便是一个母亲能够有的最好的最大的安慰」
“That is the biggest comfort a mother can get.”
「孩子的才干，得到了世界人类的知道」
“Let the world know the talent of your children.”
「父母愿意做什么的东西都得」
“Parents will do anything for that.”
「于是我写了这忽然间的信给你」
“That is why I write you this sudden letter.”
「虽然你不知道我是什么微细的东西」
“Although you don't know humble things like me.”
「但我的孩子很大，很大！」
“But my boy is big, very big.”
「有一天，你都会知道」
“One day, you will know him too.”
「多谢合作！」
“Thank you for your cooperation.”
「你忠实的，麦太」
“Yours faithfully, Mrs. Mc”
睇完妈妈封信后
After reading mother's letter…
我决定返长洲继续捡包山
I go back to Cheung Chau to practice.
我唔系为咗见珊珊
Not because of San San.
我唔知点解要抢嗰啲包
I don't know why I want to snatch a bun.
我亦唔信抢包山会成为奥运项目
And I don't think it will ever become an Olympic item.
但系，我依然努力练习抢包山
But I keep learning.
因为，我爱我妈妈
Because I love my mother.
师傅话我嘅攀爬功夫已经唔错
Master thinks my crawling has passed.
可以开始教我「十二路抢包手」
Now I'll learn the “12 Bun Snatching Hands”.
师傅话当年师祖要出呢套
Master says these 12 hands,
「十二路抢包手」⋯
in its prime…
连林世荣睇见都大赞好
was much admired by Butcher Lin!
后来麦唛话我知⋯
Later, I learn from McMug…
林世荣即系猪肉荣，系黄飞鸿嘅徒弟
Butcher Lin was a disciple of the great Kung Fu king.
我唔知到师傅似唔似黄飞鸿
I don't know much about Kung Fu kings…
但系我就肯定似旧猪肉
But I must be the ultimate pork…
我就系一个揸住两个包
The pork that struts about
喺长洲转嚟转去嘅猪肉
with buns in hands.
我一边练习，一边乱练，一边谂嘢；始终⋯
My mind boggles as I practice, after all…
我都唔系咁钟意抢包
I am not a fan of bun snatching.
我净系爱我妈妈
I am only doing this for mother.
于是我咬实牙根⋯
Hence I hang on…
一步一步，一爪一爪⋯
Step by step, claw by claw…
最后我终于练成「十二路抢包手」啦
I make it past the “12 Bun Snatching Hands”.
“There is no deformity, but saves us from a dream”
喂，我系麦兜啊
This is Dull.
正话嗰个系细路仔麦兜，我系大个佬麦兜
Dull the big guy, not Dull the boy.
细路仔麦兜同大个佬麦兜除咗把声唔同之外⋯
The two Dulls have different voices, and then…
细路仔麦兜嘅世界仲有好多幻想
Dull the boy's world is still filled with fantasy…
仲有好多希望
Filled with hopes.
希望⋯失望⋯
Hope… Disappointment…
希望⋯
Hope…
失望
Disappointment.
搞咗一轮，就变咗大个佬麦兜
On and on, he became Dull the big guy.
不过，而家我都系想讲返细路仔麦兜
But I shall tell more about Dull the boy.
细路仔麦兜仲系希望希望⋯
Dull the boy hoped a lot.
希望真系有圣诞老人
He hoped there WAS a Santa Claus.
仲系好想好想试下圣诞火鸡嘅滋味
And he hoped to eat a Christmas turkey.
系啊，我嗰阵我真系仲未食过火鸡
Right, I haven't eaten any turkey then.
所有关于火鸡嘅嘢⋯
Everything about turkey…
圣诞树一闪一闪嘅灯饰
The sparkling tinkling Christmas tree…
就好似喺天上面落嚟嘅星星噉
Like stars falling from the sky…
落喺火炉旁边
Coming down by the fireplace.
一片一片比窗外面嘅雪仲要白嘅鸡胸肉⋯
Each slice of meat looks purer than snow.
就喺我哋面前啦
Right in front of us…
香气直入灵魂⋯
The aroma attacks our soul…
就连守喺灵魂旁边嘅天使都醒咗起嚟
Waking even the guardian angels.
围住呢一嚿好香好香又好圣洁嘅肉⋯
Who float around the aromatic and holy dish…
喺圣诞夜里面飞呀，飞呀⋯
Floating in the Christmas night, floating…
但系呢一切一切关于火鸡嘅嘢，都不过系我嘅想像
All this about turkey was only my imagination.
因为我从来都未食过火鸡⋯
I had never eaten a turkey.
就连嗰阵味都未闻过
I had never even smelt one.
妈妈话火鸡太大
Mother claimed turkey was too big.
我哋一家两口，点食都食唔晒
The two of us would never finish it.
有一年圣诞节妈妈买咗半边烧鸭庆祝
One Christmas we celebrated with roast duck.
当时我，真系十分十分之失望
I was really, really disappointed.
又有一年，有间大百货公司倒闭
Another year, she bought a mini-oven at 60% off…
妈妈用四折买咗个焗炉仔返屋企
At a closedown sale.
可能系因为买咗焗炉而技痒
Thanks to the oven…
嗰日妈妈竟然同我讲⋯佢话⋯
Mother decided one day…
明日我哋要超级市场揪火鸡
We would go shopping for a turkey.
我同妈妈揪住只火鸡行返屋企嗰阵，喺嗰阵时⋯
On the way home, with turkey in hand…
我谂系我生命里面最开心嘅一刻
That was the happiest moment in my life.
火鸡终于解冻啦
The turkey was ready.
我同妈妈，噉双手搽满盐⋯
Following mother, with salt on both hands…
喺火鸡丰厚嘅鸡胸度，起细噉擦擦
I rubbed the turkey's thick chest.
联火鸡时⋯
When sewing up…
妈妈一个唔觉意畀酿喺火鸡里面嘅洋葱粒漏咗出嚟
Some of the stuffing…
红萝卜粒
leaked out.
我话：火鸡「疴烂煮」呀！
I cried: the turkey's stomach won't stop!
火鸡好勉强塞咗入焗炉度
We managed to stuff the turkey into the oven.
12月24日
24th, December
上升嘅白烟同奇异嘅焦味拨动星星
Rising smoke stirred the stars with a crunchy smell.
个焗炉戚戚恻恻，戚戚恻恻⋯
The oven hummed. Hummed.
就好似天使预早畀我哋嘅福音
It was like early blessing from the angels.
好靓嘅夜晚呀！
Such a beautiful night!
我同妈妈坐喺尖东海旁
Mother and I sat at the seafront.
点点点点嘅灯光喺海上面走来走去⋯
Lights shimmered on the sea.
又靓又温柔
Beautiful and gentle.
真系好靓！
So beautiful!
我从未食过咁浓味嘅嘢
I had never tasted anything so strong.
连烧鸭连杯面都冇咁浓嘅味道
Cup noodles or roast duck were not as strong.
火鸡嘅味道喺我嘅每一个味蕾度缠住⋯
The taste embedded every single taste bud…
爆发⋯缠住⋯爆发⋯
Then exploded.
就好似今晚嘅嘢噉
Like everything tonight…
最靓最靓，最犀利，亦都系最温柔
Most beautiful, brilliant, and tender.
第二日我瞓到好晏⋯
I woke up late the next day.
刷完牙我仲感觉到火鸡嘅美味
The sweetness was still there after washing.
因为早餐食得晏⋯
As we had a late breakfast…
午餐妈妈净系整咗罐粟米汤畀我
There was only corn soup for lunch.
我系噉用匙羹撩下撩下
I idly found diced turkey…
我竟然撩到一粒美味嘅火鸡肉
in the soup.
嗰晚唔使讲，当然系我渴望咗⋯
That night finally came the long awaited…
好耐好耐好耐好耐嘅⋯圣诞火鸡大餐！
Christmas turkey dinner!
一片一片嘅火鸡肉伴碟嘅有薯仔同节瓜⋯
Slices of meat, accompanied by gourd and potato…
上面淋咗一层老抽生粉献
were dressed with soy sauce.
我哋真系好兴奋，好满足
It was an exciting, satisfactory moment for us.
之后，我哋仲食咗一个礼拜嘅⋯
The following week,
火鸡三文治做早餐
turkey sandwich for breakfast.
星期日
Sunday,
我大着胆同妈妈讲：不如饮茶
I boldly suggested eating out.
妈妈闹我「冇衣食」⋯
Mother said I was ungrateful…
但系都带咗我去饮茶
But took me out anyway.
之后，妈妈又有计⋯
Then mother got inspired again.
佢将雪柜净返嘅火鸡肉系噉撕系噉撕
What was left of the turkey was sliced…
有时都叫我帮手撕
with me helping out at times.
火鸡留喺指甲嗰阵味
It was not easy to get rid of…
原来洗好多次都仲喺度㗎
the turkey's smell.
银芽火鸡丝炒米，好味道噉
Fried noodle with sliced turkey, yummy.
栗子焖火鸡丝煲
Steaming chestnut bowl with sliced turkey.
花生火鸡骨煲粥
Peanut congee with turkey bone.
纸包火鸡包包纸
Paper turkey bun.
包火鸡包包包火鸡包
Paper turkey paper bun.
酿火鸡馅搽面包
Turkey pâté with bread.
唉，我后悔讲过「火鸡疴烂煮」呢句嘢
I shouldn't have said anything about the turkey's stomach.
到端午节，当我督开我最钟意食嘅裹蒸粽嘅时候⋯
Came Dragon Boat Festival, when I dug into the dumpling…
发现宿喺咸蛋旁边嘅系一件火鸡背脊⋯
And found more pieces of turkey…
我脑部一时想唔通，喊咗起上嚟
I lost it. I cried.
救命啊！
Oh please!
妈妈静鸡鸡将净低嘅火鸡撇咗
When mother finally disposed of the turkey…
原来嗰阵已经系只火鸡解冻咗差唔多半年后嘅事
It was already half a year later.
我嘅美梦同噩梦都同时完结
My beautiful dream ended with my nightmare.
后来我先知道⋯
Later, I learned that…
一只火鸡由出世到畀人㓥
A serving turkey needs only to be raised…
都不过系几个月之间嘅事
for a few months.
即系话，只火鸡死咗之后同我哋一齐嘅日子
The time the turkey spent with us…
仲长过佢自己本身条命
was in fact longer than its life.
我仲发觉到，火鸡嘅味道⋯
I realized also, with turkey…
未食同食第一啖之间已经系佢嘅最高峰
taking the first bite is all that matters.
之后，不过都系食开就食埋落去噉解
Afterwards, it is just “be over and done with it”.
我冇哲学家嘅头脑⋯
I am no philosopher.
唔知呢两样嘢要得出啲咩道理
I could not come up with any profundity.
但系呢啲谂法⋯
But, such thoughts…
喺我长大之后⋯
After I grew up…
系一啲同圣诞节无关嘅日子⋯
On days unrelated to Christmas…
无端端噉喺我脑部出现过两三次
Did come up again a couple of times.
一次，喺我自己嘅婚宴上
Once, it was at my wedding.
一次⋯
Once…
喺我妈妈火化嗰日
It was at my mother's cremation.
嗰日，我望住天空几条灰色嘅烟
That day, I was looking at the smoke rising up.
忽然闻到火鸡又浓又淡嘅气味
Suddenly, the smell of the turkey returned.
我后悔要妈妈撇咗几件火鸡
I regretted I made mother throw the turkey away.
特别报道
“Special Report”
奥运滑浪风帆金牌得主李丽珊决定参加今届嘅奥运
Olympic medal winner San San Li will compete again…
向全世界人再次证明⋯
To prove to the world that…
香港嘅运动员唔系腊鸭
HK athletes are horrible.
另一方面⋯
Also…
中国香港体育协会暨奥委会会长霍震霆⋯
The local federation…
正式向亚运协会提出申请
officially announced today:
香港将要争夺下届亚运会嘅主办权
HK will apply to host the Asian Games.
多个运动团体立即表示热烈支持
Response from all sides has been enthusiastic.
其中港九新界竹战联谊会⋯
Among them, the Bamboo Game Association…
更希望打麻雀可以成为亚运项目
is proposing Mahjong for official game.
另外，全港茶餐厅员工协会⋯
While Tearoom Serving Groups…
经已发动所有会员⋯
have vowed…
争取「掟蛋挞」成为亚运会比赛项目
To campaign for “Tart Throwing”.
港九烧味卤味腊味同业会
As for the Cold Cut and Roasting Association…
亦都向霍主席当面提出⋯
They believe…
「挂腊鸭」可以成为亚运比赛项目
“Duck Hanging” would make an ideal addition.
较为特别嘅系，CIC保险营业员联同⋯
More interesting, CIC Insurance is joining force with…
大角咀春田花花幼稚园⋯
Children from…
附属小学嘅一班小朋友⋯
Spring Flower Primary School…
争取「抢包山」
In support of…
一项几乎绝迹嘅运动⋯
“Bun Snatching”…
成为本港举办亚运重点推介嘅比赛项目
A game thought extinct.
最后⋯
In the end…
最后，全部都系「芭﹣娜﹣娜」
Nothing came of anything.
最后，佢哋选咗「掟蛋挞」做推介项目
“Tart Throwing” was chosen as the highlight.
至于香港争取申办亚运嘅口号⋯
As for the official slogan…
亦都顺理成章噉叫做「香港一蛋挞」
“HK, One Big Tart” was a logical choice.
之后李丽珊蝉联失败⋯
Then San San Li lost.
亚运主办权⋯
And the hosting right of the Asian Games…
亦都由一个香港人从未听过嘅地方夺得
Went to a place Hong Kong people have never heard of.
谂住可以转行做运动员嘅茶餐厅伙计⋯
Tearoom workers, those aspiring athletes…
都返返去茶餐厅继续掟佢哋嘅蛋挞
Went back to where they used to throw their tarts.
一切回复正常
Everything went on as usual.
上个中学，我已经再冇练习抢包手
In secondary school, I stopped practicing the 12 hands.
间中同妈妈饮茶⋯
Sometimes, when I went out with mother…
我都会手快快噉帮佢抢个笼大包
I'd still snatch a bun for her.
之后，茶楼都冇卖大包
Then they stopped selling buns.
推车仔都转咗用点心纸
Carts were replaced by ordering sheets.
一切都落空
Everything came to nothing.
有时我都会同班同学仔返长洲烧嘢食
At times, I'd go to Cheung Chau for barbecue.
每次见到师傅⋯
The master looked older…
佢都好似老咗啲噉
Each time I saw him.
因为环保⋯
For environmental reasons…
长洲嘅抢包经已转咗用塑胶
They'd changed to snatch plastic buns.
师傅话，嗰阵胶气，都几臭下
Master thought they stunk.
长洲有个张保仔洞
On Cheung Chau was a Cheung Po Tsai Cave.
听讲海盗张保仔喺里面收埋咗好多宝藏
Where legend claimed the pirate hid his treasure.
因为我练过抢包手，身手比较灵活⋯
As I was the one who could crawl…
班同学叫我爬去睇下，话唔定会发达
My mates said I should take a look and maybe get rich.
于是我就向住呢一个又黑又窄嘅洞⋯
So I crawled along the dark and narrow cave.
系噉爬爬
Crawling.
洞里面乜都冇，净系有一个盒
There was nothing but a box.
我好小心揭开呢个盒⋯
I opened the box…
发现入面系一个食剩咗嘅大包
Inside, there was an unfinished bun.
唔知系咪张保仔食净㗎啦？
Maybe the pirate didn't get to finish it.
「寻晚，食了六个餐包」
“Eating 6 buns last night…”
「可惜我依然系觉得仍未十分饱」
“Still left me hungry.”
「寻晚，食了磅半方包」
“Eating 1½lb white bread last night…”
「可叹是我依然觉得，不够顶肚」
“Still left me hungry.”
「年少，练了六套脚法。」
“Excelled 6 sets of steps when I was young…”
「可惜我依然未觉够用。」
“Still left me empty.”
「年晚，又培育了珊珊！可惜⋯」
“Brought up San San when I am old! Still…”
揸住个包，我忽然明白⋯
Bun in hand, I suddenly realized…
原来有啲嘢，冇就真系冇
There are things that cannot be forced.
唔得，就真系唔得
A no is a no.
冇鱼蛋冇粗面冇去马尔代夫⋯
No fishball, no noodle, no Maldives…
冇奖牌冇张保仔宝藏
No medal, no pirate's treasure.
而张保仔，亦都冇咬过个包
And the pirate took no bite.
原来蠢，唔系咁好笑
Stupid is not funny.
蠢会失败⋯
Stupid leads to failure…
会失望
To disappointment.
失望，唔系咁好笑
Disappointed is not funny.
肥，都未必好笑
Fatness is not funny too.
肥，唔一定大力
Fatness is not powerful.
大力，亦都唔一定得
Power doesn't mean yes.
揸住个包，我忽然喺度谂⋯
Bun in hand, I suddenly thought…
大个咗，到我要面对呢一个实掘掘⋯
Growing up, facing this sordid world…
未必到你发梦，又未必咁好笑嘅⋯
This not so dreamy, not so funny world…
世界嘅时候，我会系点㗎呢？
What shall I be?
「⋯无力挽！」
“…Nothing shall be done!”
“Fat, Still”
橙
“Powerful”
系呀，我就系大个佬麦兜喇
Right, I am McDull the big guy.
肥啰，算大力啦
Fat, with raw power.
麻麻地得咁啦
Not doing too well.
负家产啰
Negative property.
脚瓜真系几大，仲大过个节瓜
With a pair of really thick calves.
脚瓜上面个肌肉非常结实⋯
Very muscular…
啲青筋一条一条凸下凸下，好似钢筋
With steely veins running down.
至于脚趾公啲脚甲⋯
As for the toenails…
有次我无无聊聊真系走去卡下佢⋯
I got bored one time and stared at it…
哗，足足成寸咁厚
They're tough, no kidding!
系呀，故事讲完喇
Yes, the story ends here.
呢个系一个尝试
This is a try.
失败⋯尝试⋯
Error… Try…
好多包⋯但系冇包保成功嘅故事
No guarantee that one would make it.
故事讲咗一轮⋯
In the end…
乜都冇？又唔系噃
Zero gain? Not really.
就系大咗两个脚瓜
I have my calves.
但系冻住两个脚瓜企喺度⋯
But, standing here like this…
当啲浪打埋嚟⋯
When the waves hit…
嗰种感觉真系好好
I feel great.
你知我麻麻地叻佬，唔识得⋯
You see, smart guys like me don't really know…
帮自己嘅故事加啲教训呀锦囊呀嗰啲嘢
How to make a lesson out of his own story.
但系，冻住两个脚瓜企喺水嗰度⋯
With calves in water…
当风吹喺我个脑部，我会谂⋯
When the wind blows, I'd think…
如果妈妈见到我呢个大脚瓜⋯
If mother could see me like this…
我谂，佢会好开心
She'd be happy.
都系唔好呀，都系出返个锦囊先得！
I've come up with a lesson!
妈妈嘅 dot com 散咗之后，佢又有计喇
Mother got inspired after her dot com failed.
佢出咗本教煮餸嘅食谱，咁煮喇饭咋晒
She published a cookbook.
食谱最后一页系教人整烧鸡嘅
The last recipe was “Roast Chicken”.
方法简单，人人都学得识
A simple dish no less.
「烧鸡」
“Roast Chicken”.
材料系⋯鸡
Ingredient: chicken.
方法：攞只鸡去烧佢几烧
Method: roast the chicken.
就噉，一味「烧鸡」就大功告成喇
That way, you have a roast chicken.
食谱度又补充噉话：
There was a remark in the cookbook:
如果想你个鸡烧得美味可口⋯
If you want a delicious chicken…
冇话食完腰心腰肺顶住个胃
A chicken that wouldn't upset you…
个秘诀系：唔该，烧得佢好啲啰⋯
The secret is: please, roast it well!
多谢合作！
Thank you!
唔该，我要一个常餐啦
One Regular, please.
常餐？常餐有咩食㗎？
What's a Regular?
同特餐一样啰
The same as Special.
噉特餐系咩嚟㗎？
What's a Special?
同快餐咁上下啰
Same as Quickie.
噉快餐又系咩嚟㗎？
What's a Quickie?
啫快餐咪就係午餐
A Quickie is a Lunch.
午餐食咩㗎？
What's for Lunch?
午餐同晚餐一样㗎
The same as Supper.
噉晚餐又食啲咩呀？
What's for Supper?
晚餐咪真系常餐啰
Same as Regular.
噉呀，我要两个常餐啦
We'll have the Regular.
好嘢呀，我哋今日啲常餐！
Our Regular today is fantastic!
唔好意思，常餐卖晒
Sorry, Regular is gone.
咁改要特餐啦
We can have the Special.
特餐？特餐有咩食㗎？
What's a Special?
特餐就即系午餐啰
A Special is a Lunch.
午餐食乜嘢㗎？
What's for Lunch?
都系晚餐嗰啲嘢啰
What you get for Supper.
咁乜嘢系晚餐呀？
What's for Supper?
同快餐一样啰
Same as Quickie.
咁快餐食咩㗎？
What's for Quickie?
系，快餐就即系常餐啰
A Quickie is a Regular.
咁你头先又话冇常餐？
But you said Regular is gone!
系呀，常餐就系卖晒呀，咁你试唔试下特餐啦？
Regular sure is gone. How about the Special?
两份特餐啦
It's the Special, then.
唔好意思，特餐卖晒嘅
Sorry, Special is gone.
妈妈，不如改快餐啦
Mother, let's have the Quickie.
快餐有咩㗎？
What's for Quickie?
快餐即系常餐
A Quickie is a Regular.
咁常餐有咩㗎？
What's for Regular?
常餐就即系午餐啰
A Regular is a Lunch.
哎呀，咁午餐有咩食呀？
What's for Lunch?
午餐同晚餐一样㗎
Same as Supper.
咁晚餐呢？
And Supper?
晚餐就即系特餐啰
Supper is like Special.
咁你头先又话冇特餐？
But you said the Special is gone.
系呀，特餐系卖晒呀，咁你试唔试下个快餐啦？一样嘅啫
The Special sure is gone. Try Quickie. It's the same.
咁两份快餐啦
We'll have Quickie.
唔好意思，冇快餐呀
Sorry, Quickie is gone.
嚟唔嚟普啲呀？噉你哋究竟有啲咩餐呀？
This is too much! Is there anything we can eat here?
午餐啦，午餐好嘢呀
Try the Lunch. It's fantastic!
点好嘢法呀？
How so?
同晚餐一样咁好嘢
It's like the Supper.
噉晚餐又点好嘢法呀？
What about the Supper?
同常餐一样咁好嘢啰
It's like the Regular.
噉常餐又点好嘢法呀？
And what about the Regular?
常餐，常餐一早卖晒啦，你话好唔好嘢？
The Regular is gone. Isn't that fantastic?
好啦好啦！要两份午餐啦
Great! We'll have Lunch.
唔好意思，午餐卖晒
Sorry, Lunch is gone.
试唔试下我哋嘅晚餐啦？一样嘅啫
Try our Supper. It's all the same.
日光日白，食乜鬼嘢晚餐啊？
I'm not having supper under broad daylight!
系，个名叫晚餐啫，其实咪就係午餐？
What's in a name? It's the same as Lunch.
好啦好啦，怕咗你啦！要两份晚餐啦！快啲手啊！
Great! Whatever you say! And make it quick!
想快？想快就要快餐啊！
You want it quick? Try Quickie!